An Arab and a Jew walk into an Escape Room.
دخل عربي ويهودي "غرفة النجاة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, it sounds like a joke.
صحيح، تبدو وكأنها نكتة.
What do they feel?
ماذا سيكون شعورهما؟
Fear?
خوف؟
Negative stereotypes?
صور نمطية سلبية؟
Mistrust? Conflict?
عدم ثقة؟ صراع؟
Probably.
على الأرجح.
But, what do they have actually in common?
لكن الأشياء المشتركة بينهما فعلاً
Quite a lot.
كثيرة جداً.
They won't be able to escape from imprisonment
لن يتمكنا من الفرار من السجن
unless they interact, cooperate and figure together a way out.
إن لم يتحادثا ويتعاونا ليجدا معاً طريقة للفرار.
This is exactly what we do.
هذا بالضبط ما نفعله.
We bring people living in a conflict zone together,
نجمع أشخاصًا يعيشون في مناطق النزاع،
through an online gameplay,
ومن خلال اللعب عبر الإنترنت
putting aside fear, negative stereotypes and mistrust,
يتخلّون عن الخوف والصورالنمطية السلبية وانعدام الثقة،
and communicating, collaborating, and even becoming friends.
ومن ثم يتواصلون ويتعاونون، بل وحتى يصبحون أصدقاء.
However, conflicts are not exclusive to our region.
لكن النزاعات ليست مقتصرة على منطقتنا.
Conflicts are everywhere.
النزاعات تحدث في كل مكان.
Conflicts are awful.
النزاعات مريعة،
They affect the quality of life in every society and city involved.
وهي تؤثر على نوعية الحياة في كل مجتمع أو مدينة تحدث فيها.
Living in a conflict zone and being a father,
كوني أب يعيش في منطقة نزاع
I have been restless, concerned and worried for many years.
بقيت ولسنين مضطربًا وقلقًا.
Some of you share the same concerns, worries,
بعضكم يشاركني نفس الهم والقلق،
and maybe attempts
ولربما حاولتم
to figure out ways to bring some good to our future.
إيجاد طرق لتحقيق مستقبل أفضل.
Many have tried different programs, yet many have failed.
جرّبَ العديد برامج مختلفة، لكن الكثير منها فشل.
You've probably experienced, for example,
لعلكم جربتم، على سبيل المثال،
some Arab-Jewish dialogue programs conducted at schools.
بعض برامج الحوار العربي اليهودي في المدارس.
Honestly, none of them really work,
بصراحة، لم يُفلح أي منها
make a change,
في إحداث تغيير
or create true friendships.
أو خلق صداقات حقيقية.
I felt we don't have a privilege to sit aside,
شعرتُ أننا لا نملك خيار الجلوس مكتوفي الأيدي،
none of us has.
لا يملك أي منّا هذا الخيار.
And we cannot wait for politicians to bring any good to our region.
كما أننا لا نستطيع انتظار السياسيين ليجلبوا الخير للمنطقة.
We cannot wait and we should not wait.
لا نستطيع الانتظار، ويجب ألا ننتظر.
Being a father,
لكوني أب
I learn a lot -
تعلمت الكثير...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
from my kids, my nephews, my family.
من أولادي وأولاد إخوتي وأخواتي وعائلتي.
A while ago, I had an amazing observation.
قبل فترة لاحظت شيئاً رائعاً.
I've noticed my kid,
لاحظت أن ابني
my son and my nephews,
وأبناء اخوتي وأخواتي
having a loud phone conversation
يتحدثون عبر الهاتف بصوت عال
while playing on their iPads.
أثناء اللعب بأجهزة الآيباد.
I've realized that they were aligning moves with relatives abroad
أدركت أنهم كانوا ينظمون التحركات مع أقربائهم في الخارج
while playing an online video game with them.
أثناء اللعب معهم عبر الإنترنت.
This made me wonder.
أثار هذا تساؤلي.
Young people are passionate about screens and video games.
الصغار والشباب مولعون بالأجهزة وألعاب الفيديو.
They play, they interact, they enjoy -
إنهم يلعبون ويتفاعلون ويستمتعون بأوقاتهم،
sometimes they fight,
وأحياناً يتشاجرون،
but unlike most adults,
ولكنهم، بعكس أغلب الكبار،
they recover, forgive and go back to play very fast.
ينسون ويسامحون ويعودون للعب بسرعة.
And they are not fixed yet with negative stereotypes
كما أنهم لم يتشبثوا بعد بالصور النمطية السلبية
or perceptions.
أو غيرها من المفاهيم.
If online video games can bring people together,
إن كانت ألعاب الفيديو على الإنترنت تجمع الناس،
what if we utilize them
ماذا سيحدث لو أننا استخدمناها
to get people to play, interact and become friends,
لجلب الأشخاص ليلعبوا ويتفاعلوا ويصبحوا أصدقاء،
even in conflict zones?
حتى في مناطق النزاع؟
Eureka!
وجدتها!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Young gamers are damn too good.
اللاعبون الصغار ماهرون جداً.
They are great problem solvers.
إنهم رائعون في حل المشكلات.
They strive to become the best version of themselves,
هم يجاهدون كي يحسّنوا أنفسهم،
seeking a heroic win,
ويسعون لتحقيق نصر بطولي
to somehow and some extent save the world while playing.
ليتمكنوا بطريقة ما من إنقاذ العالم أثناء اللعب.
If young gamers are damn too good in solving problems in a virtual world,
إذا كان اللاعبون الصغار ماهرين في حل المشكلات في العالم الصُوَري،
are they capable of solving real problems in the real life?
أتراهم قادرين على حل مشكلات حقيقية في الحياة الواقعية؟
This led me to meet Uri and Dudi,
قادني هذا إلى لقاء أوري ودودي،
who share the same thoughts and desires
الذان شاركاني نفس الأفكار والرغبات
to utilize the language young people love, want and deserve:
للاستفادة من اللغة التي يحبها الصغار ويرغبون بها ويستحقوها:
online video games!
ألعاب الفيديو على الإنترنت.
Together, we founded Games For Peace.
وهكذا، أسسنا معاً "ألعاب من أجل السلام".
Now, the idea of utilizing online video games
آنذاك، لم تكن فكرة استخدام ألعاب الفيديو على الإنترنت
to address some of the urgent issues
للتعامل مع بعض القضايا الملّحة،
wasn't really new.
لم تكن فكرة جديدة.
In fact, many have tried to pursue this idea
في الحقيقة، حاول الكثير متابعة هذه الفكرة
by developing some designated games
بتطوير بعض الألعاب المُصمَمة خصيصاً
aiming at dialogue, conflict resolution and peace promotion.
لتشجيع الحوار وحل النزاعات والترويج للسلام.
Maybe you've heard of such games.
لعلكم سمعتم بمثل هذه الألعاب.
These games could be great as an experiment,
قد تكون هذه الألعاب رائعة كاختبار،
but none of them is actually famous, scalable, or even popular.
لكنها ليست مشهورة على نطاق واسع أو ذات شعبية.
Instead of developing designated games,
فبدل أن نطوّر ألعاب مصمَمَة لهذا الغرض،
we are exploiting the great appeal of mass popular online video games.
نحن نستثمر الجاذبية التي تتمتع بها ألعاب الفيديو ذات الشعبية الواسعة.
Minecraft.
ماينكرافت.
Minecraft is a great environment,
تمثل ماينكرافت بيئة رائعة
a game where communication, collaboration and creativity are prized.
حيث يتم مكافأة التواصل والتعاون والإبداع.
It's popular, and young people are addicted to it.
إنها ذات شعبية واسعة والصغار مدمنون على لعبها.
Did you know that over 40 million gamers play Minecraft every month?
هل تعرفون أن أكثر من 40 مليون لاعب يلعبون ماينكرافت كل شهر؟
Minecraft has today over 100 million users around the world.
اليوم، يلعب ماينكرافت أكثر من 100 مليون لاعب حول العالم.
If they all go live to play together,
لو أنهم اجتمعوا ليلعبوا معاً على الهواء،
that would make them one of the largest countries in the world.
لشكلّوا واحدة من أكبر دول العالم.
Together with our developers,
عملنا مع المبرمجين العاملين لدينا
we took Minecraft and changed its settings
على تغيير البيئة داخل لعبة ماينكرافت
to meet our needs.
لتلبي حاجاتنا.
We created a new look and feel,
وخلقنا شكلاً وشعوراً جديداً،
a new gameplay,
كأنها لعبة جديدة،
and gave players more features without imposing any agenda.
وأضفنا مواصفات أكثر للاعبين من دون فرض أية أهداف مسبقة.
Remember the Escape Room?
هل تتذكرون "غرفة النجاة"؟
This is how our gameplay begins.
هكذا بدأت لعبتنا.
Our gameplay requires players to talk, to collaborate,
تتطلب لعبتنا من اللاعبين أن يتحدثوا ويتعاونوا،
to align moves, to become allies.
وأن ينظموا تحركاتهم وأن يتحالفوا.
Can you imagine young people from all across the Middle East
هل يمكنك أن تتصور صغار من جميع أنحاء الشرق الأوسط
coming to play Minecraft together?
يجتمعون كي يلعبوا لعبة ماينكرافت؟
We did it!
نحن حققنا ذلك!
It was very exciting to see young gamers
كان من المثير والممتع أن نرى لاعبين صغار
from Israel, Palestine, Jordan, Saudi Arabia, Tunisia and Iran -
من إسرائيل وفلسطين والأردن والسعودية وتونس وإيران،
yes, Iran -
نعم، إيران،
coming to play Minecraft together.
مجتمعين ليلعبوا ماينكرافت سوية.
Teenagers came to play, came to do, what they like most,
جاء المراهقون ليلعبوا ويفعلوا ما يحبون:
to play games they love.
ليلعبوا ألعاباً يحبونها.
And they came back to play again and again,
ثم عادوا ليلعبوا مرة تلو الأخرى
and inspired more gamers to join.
مما شجع المزيد من اللاعبين على الانضمام إليهم.
For them, it's Minecraft.
بالنسبة لهم، هي ماينكرافت.
For us, it's a radical new way of bridging the gaps
بالنسبة لنا، هي طريقة ثورية جديدة لمّد الجسور
between different sectors in a conflict zone.
بين قطاعات مختلفة في مناطق النزاع.
Now, you're probably wondering,
لعلكم تتساءلون الآن،
if each one comes from a different country,
إن كان كل منهم قد جاء من بلد مختلف
how did they manage to communicate?
كيف استطاعوا التواصل فيما بينهم؟
Well, technology is not an issue.
حسناً، لم تكن هذه التكنولوجيا صعبة.
We've managed to embed an instant translation chat engine
تمكنّا من إدخال آلية للترجمة الفورية للحوارات
into our game,
في داخل اللعبة،
so everyone enjoys playing without any lingual barriers.
كي يستمتع الجميع باللعب من دون أية حواجز لغوية.
Amazingly, social media was great in spreading our message.
ولعبت وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي دوراً رائعاً في نشر رسالتنا.
Our program was embraced by young gamers in Georgia and Abkhazia.
استقبل برنامجنا لاعبين صغار في جورجيا وأبخازيا.
It was also conducted between Spanish and Basque gamers
كما استخدمه لاعبون في مباراة بين إسبانيا والباسك
at the Basque Museum.
جرت في متحف الباسك.
Look at them.
انظروا إليهم.
Isn't it great to enjoy a game you love
أليس من الرائع أن تستمتع بلعبة تحبها،
and, at the same time, break down historical walls of hate and mistrust,
وفي ذات الوقت تهدم جدراناً تاريخية من الكراهية وانعدام الثقة،
giving peace a real chance?
وتعطي السلام فرصة حقيقية؟
Today, our program is running at schools in Israel,
اليوم، يُستَخدَم برنامجنا في مدارس في إسرائيل
bringing young Arabs and Jews to play Minecraft together,
حيث يجتمع عرب ويهود صغار ليلعبوا لعبة ماينكرافت سوية،
and to get to know each other better.
وليتعرفوا على بعضهم بشكل أفضل.
They play online,
إنهم يلعبون عبر الإنترنت
and, after several sessions, they meet offline, face to face,
وبعد عدة مرات يلتقون وجهاً لوجه،
and they enjoy it a lot.
وهم يستمتعون بذلك كثيراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The program is so appealing
صار للبرنامج شعبية كبيرة
the teachers are asking us to participate and have their own gameplay.
حتى صار المعلمون يطلبون أن يعملوا معنا كي يكون لديهم لعبة خاصة بهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We're speaking of a real measurable change
نحن نتحدث عن تغيير حقيقي بالإمكان قياسه
in real time and in the real world.
في وقت حقيقي وفي العالم الواقعي.
We see more positive thoughts of the others,
صرنا نرى أفكاراً إيجابية أكثر للآخرين،
an increase in the readiness to engage with the others.
وزيادة في الاستعداد للتواصل مع الآخرين.
The potential for good is incredible.
الاستعداد الكامن للخير لا يُصدَق.
So, if you want a more comfortable present
إذن، إن كنتم تريدون حاضراً هنيئاً
and a better future -
ومستقبلاً أفضل،
I bet you all want a better future -
طبعاً كلكم يريد مستقبلاً افضل،
we need to start investing in young people,
يجب أن نبدأ بالاستثمار في الصغار،
learn from them, listen to them, interact with them.
وأن نتعلم منهم ونستمع إليهم ونتواصل معهم.
Young generations can teach us - us -
يمكن لأجيال الشباب أن تعلمنا
how to break down barriers,
كيف نزيل الحواجز،
how to accept the others around,
وكيف نتقبل الآخرين من حولنا،
how to build peace.
وكيف نعمل لتحقيق السلام.
What will happen if we trap together
ماذا سيحدث لو أننا وقعنا معاً،
an American, a North Korean, an Afghani and a Russian,
أمريكي وكوري شمالي وأفغاني وروسي،
all in one Escape Room?
في "غرفة نجاة"؟
Can online games make a difference?
هل يمكن لألعاب الفيديو أن تحدث تغييراً؟
Let's see! Let's play!
لنرى، لنلعب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً.